The Oregon Field, New Jersey, will host the first annual Father Joseph Allen Memorial
lecture.
The speaker is Dr. Gail Wula-Shack, and the topic is Orthodox Biowethics and Pastoral
Ministry.
The event begins with Vespers at 5 o'clock PM, followed by a reception at 6 and the lecture
at 7 o'clock PM.
For more information, please visit saintaneebergenfield.org.
That's saintaneebergenfield.org.
has been a public service and now...
of Ancient Faith Radio.
This is a Lord of Spirits special presentation.
So, Father Andrew and all the other ancient fake folks are at some kind of
some kind of uh...
meeting or get together or conference or retreat or
some other kind of fall-to-all.
But I did not as an independent contractor
who was not involved want our listeners to go
completely deprived of new content
on this fourth Thursday of the month of September 2022.
And so I said to myself,
Self I said what sort of content?
would appease the appetite of our listeners. And I decided that what you might want to hear,
other than three hours of me monologuing about something, would be to hear the story of a
Sumerian Wizard Dool from the 18th century BC.
So this text was written down and recorded.
In between the time of Abraham and the time of Moses, that latter part, we'll talk about a little more after I read it.
I'm only going to read part of it, the cool part with the Wizard duel.
But this text is one of a series of Sumerian texts from that era telling stories about Endmercar.
N. Merikar was the grandfather of Gilgamesh.
and the King of Iraq.
Most of these stories involve Enmercar trying to place the King of another city into a vassal position beneath him to pay him tribute.
And so, there are all of these interesting ways in which he manages to subjugate these various other cities.
So the beginning of this text which is in
entitled Enmercar and Ensu Garana.
And those get spelled in fascinatingly different ways.
But if you spell it out phonetically,
you could probably find it.
If you want to read more about it,
is about our friend Enmercar trying to subjugate,
in this case, the city of Arata, not Arata,
but Arata with an A.
And here's a little...
bit of difficulty doing it. At least it's sort of a three-step process. So it starts out with an
exchange of letters. That exchange of letters between the two kings involves a bunch of insults
and involves a series of brags, shall we say, by each king about how he has been a better
lover to the goddess whom both cities worship.
and verbally at least in the letters,
and Merckard kind of gets the upper hand in this exchange
of letters.
But that does not mean that Arada is going
to immediately submit to his authority.
And so as I pick up reading here,
I'm going to be a little euphemistic at a few places.
You'll be able to imagine why as we go along.
But Arada
is enacting a plan since and sugerano was unable to gain the upper hand in the letter exchange.
He sends a sorcerer to go and enact a plot that he believes will allow him to get the better of
and mercarr and uruk. So that is where we are picking up if there's someone out there nerdy enough
to have the critical addition of the
text, we're picking up at line 170 of this particular Sumerian epic. And so the
sorcerer, having planted the first seed, went it his way to Arresh, the city of
Nisaba. He arrived at the buyer, the place where the cows live, the cow in the
buyer trembled before him. He made the cow speak so that it conversed with him as
as if it were human.
Oh, cow, who will eat your cream? Who will drink your milk?"
The cow replied,
Nisaba will eat my cream. Nisaba will drink my milk.
And my cheese, the well-ripened shining crown,
will be properly served in the great dining hall, the dining hall of Nisaba.
For unless my cream has been brought from this splendid buyer,
unless my milk has been brought from this splendid pen,
Faithful cow Nisaba and Lil's oldest daughter cannot institute the levy.
Thank you.
So just pausing there, Nisaba is a goddess who sort of is the goddess of the city of Erish who we're talking about.
listening we're talking about. And so Nisaba is also a goddess, daughter of Enlil who was depicted
as bovine. So this cow has a sort of special connection to the local goddess.
So the sorcerer responds to the cow, cow, your cream to your glistening horn, your milk to your back.
And so the cow's cream was pulled back into its glistening horn, and its milk retreated into its back.
So the sorcerer sort of cursed the cow to retract its milk so it will not give milk.
He the sorcerer arrived at the splendid pen, the pen of Nisaba.
The goat in the pen trembled before
him. He made the goat speak so that it
conversed with him as if it were human.
Oh goat, who will eat your cream?
Who will drink your milk?
The goat replied, Nisaba will eat my cream.
Nisaba will drink my milk.
And my cheese, the well-ripened shining crown
will be properly served in the great dining hall,
the dining hall of Nisaba.
For unless my cream has been brought from this splendid
buyer, unless my milk has been brought from this splendid
pen, faithful Count Nisaba and those old as daughter cannot
Institute 11.
The sorcerer replied, Goat, you're creamed to your glistening horn, you're milked to your back,
and so the goat's cream was pulled back into its glistening horn,
and its milk retreated into its back.
Thereupon pen and buyer became a silent house aruant.
There was no milk in the cow's udders.
The calves days darkened.
The young calf was hungry and mood heart-rendingly.
There was no milk in the goat's udders.
The kids days darkened.
Both kid and goat lay down starving.
their lives bitterly the
spoke to its calf. And the goat commiserated with its kid. The holy churn remained empty,
was hungry and lay starving. Surely on that day pen and buyer had become a silent house a ruin.
The drover dropped his staff his eyes vacant and shocked. The shepherd fastened his crooked
his side weeping bitterly. The shepherd boy no longer frequented pen or buyer. He went elsewhere.
The milkman no longer cried out loudly, he went elsewhere.
Now there were...
a cowherd and a shepherd of Nisaba, sons of one mother, and reared in pen and buyer
they were.
Mashgula was the name of the former, Roudina of the latter.
At the great gate facing the rising sun, the marvel of the land, both of them crouched
in the dust and implored Utu in the sky.
This sorcerer, a man from Arada, broke into the pens, and the pens he caused a shortage
of milk, even the calves do not get any.
And pen and buyer he brought misery.
He made scarce-
cream and milk, he casts their doom cause their devastation. So now we have this problem,
or Enmercar has this problem because this city is one of his other vassal cities.
And so this sorcerer has been sent for Rada's special ops. He's cursed this city. They don't have any
dairy products. As a Dutchman, this is one of the most horrible fates that can befall you.
And so how is
How is, and Mercarr going to respond?
He is going to respond, and there's a little bit of a break in the tablet here, so I'm just going to have to tell you.
He responds by sending, I'm reading a somewhat modern and politically correct translation that says,
wise woman, older translations would say which.
This is a female worker of magic who works for Enmakarr at Uruk.
He sends her to go and have this wizard
duel with the Sorcerer to settle this once and for all. And so the two of them are essentially
serving as sort of champions for their respective cities. The Wise Woman is named Saga Buuru,
and they go and they meet up, this is all from little bits and pieces in the cracked tablet.
They go and meet up at the banks of the Euphrates, which they call the river of the
gods. And so now we're going to have the showdown. We're going to have the main event, the
Wizard duel. So it begins and we're at Round Line 228, both through Fish Row, Fish
Eggs, both through Fish Eggs into the river. The sorcerer drew out a big carp but why
He buys women's Seg Buru, drew out an eagle.
The eagle caught the big carp and fled.
to the mountains. Again, they threw fish eggs into the river. The sorcerer drew out a
U with lamb, but wise women said, Buru drew out a wolf. The wolf caught the U with lamb
and dragged them to the open plain. A third time, they threw fish spawned into the river.
The sorcerer drew out a cow with calf, but wise women said, Buru drew out a lion. The
Line caught the cow with calf and took them to the reed marsh.
Earth time they threw fish eggs into the river.
The sorcerer drew out an eye-bax in a wild sheep.
But why is woman's egg-buru drew out a mountain lion?
The mountain lion caught the eye-bax in the wild sheep and dragged them to the mountains.
A fifth time they threw fish spawn into the river.
The sorcerer drew out a young gazelle.
But why is woman's egg-buru drew out a tiger and a nim lion?
The tiger and the nim lion caught the young gazelle and dragged it to the woods.
the sources.
darkened, and his mind was in turmoil. Then wise women said,
Boo-ru spoke to him, O sorcerer, for all your magic lore, do you not understand anything?
How could you go to Errash the city of Nisaba? The city whose fate was fixed by
on and in will? The primeval city, the city well loved by Ninh Lil. In order to
work your evil magic, how did you dare? The sorcerer replied, I went there without
knowing what I did. Now I acknowledge your authority. Please do not-
be angry. He did obeisance. He pleaded with her.
Let me go, sister. Let me go. Let me return safely to my city. Let me go back and harm to
Arata the mountain of the Inviolet Powers. I will proclaim your greatness in all countries.
I will sing your praise in Arata the mountain of the Inviolet Powers."
Wise women said, Boo-Roo replied to him,
In pen and fire you brought misery, you made scarce cream and milk. You abolished lunch,
breakfast and dinner meals.
You cut off cream and milk from the supper in the great hall.
Misery.
Your sin of withholding cream and milk cannot be overlooked.
King Nana granted everlasting milk in the buyer.
Therefore your sin is a capital offense.
I cannot grant you life."
Wisewoman said Buru confirmed her statutory verdict on the sorcerer.
She threw down her victim on the bank of the Euphrates, took away his vital force, and
returned this to her city-arish.
So after this...
She having not only defeated the sorcerer in the Wizard's duel, but having killed him on the
Bank of the Euphrates, that vital force there is a translation of the word basically for soul.
She ripped his soul out, pulled a shang sum. At this point then the king of Arata, he's got nothing.
So he goes ahead and submits and becomes a vassal of Enmercar.
So of all the
Strange Sumerian tales I could have read for this. Why did I read this one? Well this one is some
of you might have detected is kind of interesting because it shows us sort of this paradigm
for ancient wizard doles and you might have noticed something familiar about it in terms of
the contests that happens between Moses and Janice and Jambras in Egypt. Of course the names
Come from...
from Second Temple Jewish literature
and are referenced by St. Paul,
the names for the wizards of Pharaoh who can test with Moses.
Remember, there is this whole element there
of them summoning animals.
And Moses is animals being larger and more powerful,
like the snakes and devouring them.
Right?
And so this is, as you can see, a motif, right?
The particular magic they work,
Like they're not throwing fireballs and lightning.
bolts at each other, like battle wizards, but they are using fish row, right? They're
using fish eggs and the waters of the Euphrates to create animals, to create living creatures
that then battle each other. And in every case, it's unclear whether they were picking
the animals because if they were directly picking the animals, the saucer was kind of
way. It is.
choices, but that might not be the case. It may have been just a general
sort of expression of their power or something, what kind of animal it was.
And the wise woman may have just been a little more powerful. It's hard to
totally track. But this motif of sort of wizards or sorcerers or wise
people doing battle by the summoning of creatures, there is that biblical
parallel so hopefully this brief story time will tide you
over. Tell our next episode, Lord willing, on the second Thursday of October when, again,
Lord willing, we'll be live again.
We are saved by the Lord, the way man is saved, the way man is saved.
We are loved by the Lord.
Transforming our lives in Christ.
Meditations, sermons, classes and lectures from Saint Spirit on Greek Orthodox Church in